Naruto…
《サスケ : ナルト 今度こそ消え去れ！
Just disappear already…
俺との つながりとともに！》
and take our bond along with you!
((イルカ : サスケの勝利。
Sasuke wins!
では互いに和解の印を。
All right, you two…
make the Unison Sign.
(フン！
やんのか？ 落ちこぼれが))
You wanna piece of me, you loser?
これは？
What is this?
((サスケ お前と俺が戦えば→
Sasuke…
If you and I fight…
(２人とも 死ぬ))
We'll both...
die.
死んだ？
Am I dead?
この感覚ってば…。
This sensation…
そういうことなんだろうな。
It must be…
たぶん。
Probably.
惨めだな。
うん？
Pitiful, isn't it?
お前は 九尾。
You had the Nine Tails…
俺は うちはの名によって
里から疎まれ→
and I was an Uchiha.
We were ostracized from the village
and treated like outcasts.
除け者にされていた。
そして俺たちは里を…。
And we resented the village
and its people.
里の連中を怨んだ …だろ？
Right?
((違うとは言わせねえ))
I won't let you say I'm wrong.
You called me your brother…
In that sense, perhaps we were.
お前は俺を兄弟と呼んだが→
そういう意味じゃ
確かにそうかもな。
全然違えよ。
You're totally wrong!
…と オメエ
わかってねえんだな！
Damn it,
you don't understand, do you?
悪い 綱手のばあちゃん。
Sorry, Grandma Tsunade…
絶対死なねえって
約束してたのに。
I promised…I wouldn't die…
火影になるまで。
until I became the Hokage…
あっ そうだ！ 無限月読。
Oh yeah! The Infinite Tsukuyomi!
This is bad!
やべえじゃん 俺らがいなきゃ
解術できねえんじゃねえか。
The Release Jutsu can't be activated
without us being there, right?!
死んでも まだ世界の行く末が
気になるっていうのか？
You're dead…and you're worried
about what happens to the world?
あたりめえだろ あのままで
いいわけねえだろうが。
Of course!
We can't leave it like that!
サクラとカカシがまだ残ってる。
Sakura and Kakashi still remain.
なんとかするだろ。
They'll figure something out.
だといいけど…。
I hope so.
うっ…。
ナルト？
Naruto!
火影か…。
The Hokage, huh…
((兄さんも もうすぐしたら→
Pretty soon, Big Brother, they might
carve your Great Stone Face over there!
あそこに顔岩
作ってもらえるかもね。
兄さん？
Big Brother?
(イタチ)許せ サスケ。
Forgive me, Sasuke.
This is it.
これで最後だ。
お前が これからどうなろうと→
And no matter what you do
from here on out, know this…
(俺は お前をずっと愛している))
I will love you always.
《兄さん もうすぐ会える》
Big Brother…
I'll be seeing you…soon.
やっと戻ってきたかよ。
You've finally come to, eh?
うっ…。
As you can see…
見てのとおりだ。
if either of us moves too much,
we'll bleed out and die.
お前も俺も あまり動くと
血出すぎで死ぬぞ。
Why would you go that far?
そんなになってまで
なぜ 俺の邪魔をしたがる？
Why do all that…
just to get in my way?
I gained the power to enter the darkness,
and sever all bonds…
俺は闇に入り→
すべてを切るための力を得た。
どんなやつでも当然→
And naturally, everyone's tried to cut
their ties to me as well, at some point.
そんな俺とのつながりを
一度は皆 切ろうとした。
だが お前は→
But you…
You've never attempted
to cut me off.
俺を決して切ろうとはしなかった。
The only one who can handle
all that hatred is me!
((お前の憎しみを
受けてやれんのは→
(俺しかいねえ！))
なぜ そこまでして
俺にかかわろうとする？
Why do you keep
involving yourself with me?
You already know, don't you?
もう わかってんだろ？
Now that your body can't move,
your mouth sure is moving a lot.
体が動かねえからって
やけに口がよく動くじゃ…。
Just answer me!
いいから答えろ！
'Cuz you're my friend.
友達だからだ。
What is it with you anyway?
((お前は いったい何なんだ？
I'm your friend!
友達だ。
テメエは いったい
何がしてえんだよ？
Just what the hell do you want?
Why are you so fixated on me?
なんで俺に そこまでこだわる？
It's because I'm your friend!
(友達だからだ))
それは かつて聞いた。
I've heard that before.
お前にとっての それは→
But what exactly does that mean
to you anyway?
いったい何なんだ？
それを説明しろって言われても→
You ask me to explain it,
but I really can't put it into words.
正直 俺も よくわからねえよ。
ただ… お前のそういう→
It's just that…
when I see you take on stuff…
背負って
ゴチャゴチャしてるとこ見てっと→
and get all messed up…
It kinda…
なんでか… 俺が 痛えんだ。
hurts me.
すっげえ痛くて→
It hurts so much inside,
とてもじゃねえけど→
that I can't just leave it alone, y'know?
そのまま
ほっとけねえんだってばよ。
今はさすがに あちこち痛くて
どうにもならねえけどな。
Though right now, I'm in a lot of pain
all over, and I can't do anything about it.
イテテ…。
Naruto… I knew you were
always alone back then.
《ナルト お前が昔
常に一人でいるのは知っていた。
生き残った うちはの俺と同じで→
The village shunned you,
just like they did with me…
the lone Uchiha survivor.
里で皆に阻害されていたな。
バカなことをしては
わざと叱られようとしていた。
You intentionally did stupid things
to get scolded,
他人と関わるためだろう。
most likely to get people's attention.
最初は そんなお前を見て
くだらないやつだと思った。
In the beginning, I thought
you were good for nothing.
じゃれたいだけの弱いやつだと。
A weakling who just constantly
wanted to goof around.
But the more I watched you being idiotic
and getting scolded over and over…
だが 何度も叱られているお前を
ずっと見ていると→
For some reason,
it started weighing on my mind.
なぜだか気になるようになった。
そのとき思った。
I thought back then, that your weakness
was gradually rubbing off on me.
お前の弱さが だんだん
俺に染まってきたんだと。
それからのお前を見るたびに→
Then, every time I'd see you,
I'd think about you more and more.
どんどん
気になるようになっていった。
Seeing you desperately
trying to bond with others…
他人とつながろうと
必死なお前を見ていると→
俺の家族を思い出すようになった。
made me remember my own family.
そして なぜだか 安心したんだ。
And I don't know why,
but I felt relief.
だが それは
同時に弱さだと思った。
But at the same time,
I considered it a weakness.
俺は その弱さから
逃げるように修業した。
I trained hard
as if to escape that weakness.
兄への復讐のために
兄より強くなるために。
In order to get my revenge
on my brother
to become stronger than him.
なのに
お前と同じ班になっちまった。
And yet… I ended up
on the same team as you.
And I began thinking about
my family again.
そして また家族がチラつく。
火影になりたいとほざく
お前と一緒に任務をこなし→
I went on missions with you
as you jabbered on and on
about becoming Hokage…
I saw how both of us
were getting stronger…
互いに強くなっていくのを
実感した俺は→
And one day, I started to feel
the desire to fight you too.
いつしか お前とも闘いたい
そう思うようにもなった。
そして俺は 七班に
己の家族の影を見るようになった。
And I began to see a shadow
of my own family in Squad 7…
だから
お前の苦しむ姿を見るたび→
That's why every time
I saw you suffering…
That's right…
I felt it…
そう 俺も…。
俺が痛くなったんだ。
I felt pain too.
お前の痛みがわかったとき
初めて仲間と思えた。
When I understood your hurt,
I finally saw you as a comrade.
そして その反面→
But on the other hand…
I couldn't leave you alone.
You were getting stronger and stronger.
急速に強くなっていくお前を
ほっておけなくなった。
どんどん強くなっていく
お前を見て→
Watching you steadily get stronger…
俺は…》
I…
((俺だって いつもお前が
一人なのは知ってた。
I knew that you were always alone.
すぐにでも話しかけたかった。
I wanted to walk over and start talking.
I'd get sort of giddy.
なんか 嬉しくってよ。
けど そりゃやめた。
But I stopped myself.
なんでもできるお前が
うらやましくって。
I was jealous because
you were good at everything.
So I made you my rival.
俺は勝手に
お前を俺のライバルに決めた。
お前は俺の… 目標になった。
You've been…
my goal.
何にもなかった俺が
つながりを持てた。
I had nothing, and I found a bond.
お前みたく
強く かっこよくなりたくて→
I wanted to be strong
and cool like you.
(ずっと お前の後を追いかけてた))
That's why I kept chasing after you.
《逆だ。
It was the opposite.
本当は俺が
うらやましかったんだ。
In reality, I was the one
who was jealous of you.
俺にはない強さがあったから。
Because you had a strength
that I didn't.
お前はいつも
俺の前を歩いてやがった。
You were always walking
in front of me.
まるで かつての兄さんのように。
Just like my late Big Brother.
そして 今日も…》
And…even today…
I'll let you deal with Sasuke.
((サスケはお前に任せる))
((端っから そのつもりだ。
That was my plan from the start!
(やはり お前に託して
正解だった))
Entrusting it to you was
the right thing to do, after all.
《これは… ナルトの記憶》
These are—!
Naruto's memories.
((将来の夢は… 火影を超す！
My dream…
is to surpass the Hokage one day!
んでもって 里のやつら全員に
俺の存在を認めさせてやるんだ！
And that's why I'm going to
make everyone in the village
acknowledge me!
やっぱ覚悟しとかなきゃな。
I have to be ready…
みんながみんな認めてくれる
火影ってすげえ名前語るのによ→
I'm gonna be called the Hokage,
someone that everyone acknowledges.
ぜってえ
近道なんかねえってことはよ。
There's no such thing as a shortcut!
なめんじゃねえ 俺は逃げねえぞ！
Quit messin' around,
I'll never run away!
受けてやる！
もし一生 下忍になったって→
I will make it!
Even if I stay a genin
for the rest of my life,
意地でも火影になってやるから
べつにいいってばよ！
I'll become the Hokage.
So I don't care!
まっすぐ自分の言葉は曲げねえ。
I never go back on my word.
That's my Ninja Way!
俺の忍道だ！
俺ってば お前と違って
絶対 火影の名前を受け継ぐんだ。
I'm different from you.
I'm absolutely gonna
become the Hokage.
火影は 俺の夢だから！
Becoming the Hokage
is my dream.
俺は火影になるまで
ぜってえ 死なねえからよ！
I won't die…
until I become the Hokage!
俺は どの先代をも超える
火影になる！
I'm gonna become the Hokage
to surpass all the previous ones!
それが俺の夢だ バカ野郎！
That's my dream, you idiot!
The Hokage is someone
who endures the pain
火影ってのは 痛えのを我慢して→
and takes the lead
in front of everyone.
みんなの前を歩いている
やつのことだ。
だから仲間の死体を
またぐようなことは→
So a Hokage never walks over
his comrades' corpses.
決してねえ！
There is no shortcut
to becoming the Hokage!
火影になるやつに近道はねえし→
なったやつに逃げ道はねえんだよ。
And there are no ways out
for the one who becomes Hokage!
No way can a guy who can't even
save one friend become the Hokage.
仲間一人救えねえやつが
火影になんてなれるかよ。
(そうだろ サスケ))
Isn't that right, Sasuke?
《ナルト…。
Naruto...
お前は これほどまでに…》
How far…have you—?
((イタチ : どんなに強くなろうとも→
No matter how powerful
you become,
don't try to shoulder
everything alone.
すべてを背負おうとするな。
You share your father's dream,
don't you?
お前の夢は確か父と同じだったな。
なら 覚えておけ。
Then don't ever forget…
火影になった者が
皆に認められるんじゃない。
Becoming Hokage doesn't mean
people will acknowledge you.
皆から認められた者が
火影になるんだ。
But when the people acknowledge you,
you can become Hokage.
(仲間を忘れるな))
Never forget your friends!
《兄さん…》
Big Brother…
そうか…。
I see.
Then…
それなら 見せてくれ。
show me…
どこだ？ ここ…。
Where are we?
まさか 今度こそ
マジで天国なんじゃ…。
Don't tell me this is really
Heaven this time?
どうやら 俺たちは
朝まで寝ちまったようだな。
Looks like we fell asleep
and slept until morning.
また 死に損なったようだ。
We've failed to die again.
うぅ…。
クソ… まだ 体が動かねえや。
Damn it! I still can't move!
お前 ぶん殴って 今こそ 本当に→
I was hoping to punch you hard and
make you finally open your eyes!
目 覚まさせてやろうと
思ったのに。
フフフ… ハハハハハ！
な… なんだよ？
W-What is it?
こんなになって
まだ やる気かよ？
We're messed up like this,
and you still wanna fight?
当たりめえだ！ 何度だって…。
Damn right! No matter
how many times it takes—
I admit it.
認めてやるよ。
I've…
俺の…。
負けだ。
lost.
バカ野郎！
You idiot!
この戦いは 勝ちとか負けとか
そんなんじゃねえ！
This fight isn't about winning or losing!
ダチが すねてっから
１発 ぶん殴って→
It's about punching a sulking friend,
to make him snap out of it!
目 覚ましてやろうって話だ。
That's what it's about!
The real match that I want,
comes after that!
俺のやりてぇ勝負は
そのあとだってばよ！
なぁ ナルト。
あぁ!?
Hey, Naruto…
俺は お前を認めちまった。
I just acknowledged you.
ここで 俺が死ねば→
If I die here, the long cycle of destiny
the Sage of Six Paths mentioned
六道仙人の言う
長き因縁も終わるだろう。
will probably end as well.
これも ひとつの革命だ。
This is…a kind of revolution too.
無限月読の解術は→
You can release the Infinite Tsukuyomi
after I'm dead,
俺の死後 左目を
カカシにでも移植してやればいい。
by transplanting my left eye
into Kakashi or someone else.
俺は 俺自身で
己に決着をつける。
I'll put an end to myself.
死んで…
死んで 決着つくなんて思うなよ。
By dying?
Don't think dying will settle this!
死ぬくらいなら
生きて 俺に協力しろ。
If you're willing to die,
then live and help me instead.
俺のやりたいことは
全忍の協力だ。
What I want to do is to make
all shinobi cooperate with each other.
And that definitely includes you!
もちろん お前も含めてだぞ。
お前が それでよくても
他の者は納得しない。
Just because you want tha
ったく… それ以上 すねて
グチグチ言ってみろ。
また ぶっとばすぞ！
俺が また
お前に たてつくかも わからんぞ。
そしたら また 止める！
つうか もう お前は
そんなこと しねえよ。
なぜ そう言いきれる？
これ以上 同じことを言わせんな。
お前のほうは
まだ わかってねえのかよ…。
そういや お前も
意外に バカだったもんな。
うるせぇよ… ウスラトンカチ。
ハハハッ！